It is 6 PM. Uh, I hereby call the
February 17, 2026 meeting of the City of
Cheyenne Planning Commission to order.
Staff, could you please call the role?
>> Yes.
>> Yeah.
>> Yep. Uh, Daryl Hibbons,
Lonnie Olson here via Zoom.
Bob Mati
>> here.
>> Amy Hernandez
>> present.
>> Megan Connor
>> present remotely.
>> Lloyd Wigum
which he must have went through a valley
so he might pop back in. And Tony Lair
>> here.
>> Mr. Chair, we do have a quorum.
>> Thank you. Uh we have no minutes to
approve. We usually don't do that at the
midmon meeting.
Uh I don't think anybody has any
disclosures as we don't have any
planning items tonight.
So we'll get to planning projects and
item A. You could staff start that.
Item A is the unified development code
annual review.
Um, I can give some background on the
annual annual review while we wait for
Charles because he was going to give the
presentation so I don't know all of his
notes. Um, so every year we do have the
annual review on the UDC. Um, basically
usually around December, we throw out a
press release just asking the public for
feedback and to submit
uh various annual review items that we
then look at and bring forward to you.
Um, basically at the February meeting,
usually midmon. Um, annual review is
basically open throughout the year. Uh,
it's not like it's just open from
December to January or December to
February basically. Um, it's open year
round. We take submittals year round. We
just throw the press release out
basically at the end of the year kind of
for last minute stuff. If anybody has
anything, we can pile all that and we
actually do take it to governing to the
governing body before bringing it to
planning commission. Um, so we did have
a work session with the governing body.
I want to say that was January.
still waiting for people.
>> Nope, just waiting on you.
>> Um January 23rd, I believe, is when we
had that work session. Um and that was
basically just a discussion
uh with city council about these items.
Um
and then we basically bring it to
planning commission for the formal
process that's in the UDC to kind of
discuss the annual review and basically
have planning commission give us
direction on what to move forward with
um to look at. We don't always get
through all these items. There's
probably things still on this list that
staff hasn't gotten to. Um,
but this does basically give us a list
of things that the public is interested
in. We do take the feedback from council
and planning commission to really kind
of determine what we should work on
through this next year when we have
time. Um, depending on how pressing the
certain matters are. Um and these are
various things that we look at whether
it be uh Charles will go through it but
from multif family allowances in
different zone districts are permitted
as use by right in areas
um detached versus attached sidewalk.
There's been a lot of talk of
landscaping in the past couple months
that has come up about trees. Um so
that's in in here as well. Uh but
basically we look at all these things
and then we kind of determine what can
what is going to be best for the
community. What can we put together?
What can we change in our code if
anything or add um or subtract I guess
um and then bring those forward to
planning commission and city council and
see
um if we get planning commission's
approval and then planning or uh city
council's approval to actually adopt
that. Um
I'm just buying you time. Oh, I'm ready.
I'm ready. You are.
>> So, I'm going to just go ahead and hand
it over to Director Bloom to actually
give the presentation and then I believe
with this it's mostly going to just be
kind of a discussion um on various items
and if there's anything else the
planning commission kind of wishes for
staff to look at and we can have that
discussion as well. Uh that's basically
what this process is is just discussion
on items that have come up throughout
the year.
Chair, are um Commissioner Le, are you
chair today or is uh Boyd chair?
>> I am chairing today. Boyd is perhaps on
Zoom call, but he's traveling and he's
in and out. So, we decided it would be
better if I would chair the meeting.
>> Chair, I was just double checking who
the audience was. I I saw a phone
number. I saw Lonnie and I saw
>> uh
Chair Wigum on there as well. So, good
to know with the three members on Zoom.
Um, for those of you driving, uh, don't
stare too hard at the screen. Um, I'll
try to verbally describe everything for
you.
All right,
>> this I am present.
>> All right, perfect. All right, so first
of all, I just wanted to um note that
this is going to be organized in uh a
few different this way. We have the
comments we've received from the public
through our portal that's online. We
have uh comments we've received
as of January 20 about January 19th and
early January from people that may have
been on the elected um governing body or
other electeds stuff like that that
we've heard. We've also received
comments that uh we've included comments
on a separate slide that are just
concerns we've noticed with development
reoccurring patterns we've seen. And
then we have our own little staff wish
list which is always kind of the the
last piece that we never seem to be able
to get to um during the year. So first
one is one that's been very common
throughout uh the last few years that
we've seen a push and a push nationally
and it's allowing additional density.
This is one comment we received where
it's in regard to allowing multifamily
in more places with less red tape. So,
for example, in any residential zone
district, allowing up to a forplex to be
uh permitted use by right instead of
having to go through a conditional use
approval process. So, that's one that um
seems to be gaining gathering a lot of
momentum nationwide. Um and something
like this would need to have a lot of
community outreach that would occur
because it has the ability to change a
lot of your existing neighborhoods. I do
want to note if you take an existing
structure and you do convert it into a
2unit, a 3unit, a 4unit, you're going to
have a lot of changes that are going to
need to be made on the inside, it's not
adding a door and painting some numbers
on the house. It is retrofitting the
ceiling to make sure that they have fire
separation. There's requirement that
each unit has to be able to turn off
their water supply individually instead
of a master meter. There'd also be
requirements that every unit has to be
able to control the heat and temperature
in their unit. So, you can't have
co-mingled uh HVAC systems. So, it's not
just an overnight thing. This would be
um more prevalent in newer builds where
you might see forplex developments that
would occur in new builds.
Um we've already done a little bit of
research uh regarding multifamily and
the the feelings of the community like
how they have felt. um about it. Uh this
is uh surveys that we conducted over the
course of last year. It included some at
different retailers, but also um at
Super Day was the biggest um push that
we had. Uh this survey had a lot of
folks that identified as um young
professionals um that were younger and
didn't have families, were starting on
their career. um and they had uh
indicated what what their desires were
with the survey, which we'll get to um
next. This is showing that we had 110
people do the survey. This is both
online and at Super Day. Uh
surprisingly, the young professionals
were the in-person voters and the
seniors were the ones that participated
online more. So, the seniors were online
and the young professionals were were
there. But as you look the high
prevalence there for the best reason to
have apartments for affordable housing
um choices which is the far left part of
that graph uh there's a second following
for housing for young professionals new
housing. There's a senior housing demand
that is perceived um employers looked at
housing
where there's some people that just said
there were no need for any new
apartments and some other reasons as
well. So, lots of different stuff, but
as you can see, that really comes down
to uh there was a desire for affordable
housing choices in the community because
right now there weren't weren't too many
last year. They're increasing, but there
still is a limited housing demand.
>> Director Bloom, could I could I
interrupt and just ask?
>> Definitely interrupt all you all. a
little definition maybe because I I've
read articles in the paper and so forth
with I know we had a what a task force
on affordable housing but I hear the
term attainable housing used I don't
know if it's interchangeable are those
two different things or two ways of
talking about the same thing
a little bit of both um it is more or
less the two ways talk about the same
thing a lot of folks when they hear the
words affordable housing people
automatically think that it's a section
8 housing or a different uh grouping of
folks and there's danger associated with
it when that's not true. Um, affordable
housing units by definition federally,
uh, that is for folks that are making
80% of the median income of an area.
That's your teachers, that's your
nurses, that's your your managers,
that's a lot of the city staff would
qualify for that. And I mean,
we've had people that have live in
apartments as a staff. They're okay. So,
um but attainable housing is also um
another way of phrasing that that it's
something that your typical single
individual can afford um or that the
typical family could afford which is
basically that no more than onethird of
your income goes to your housing
payments.
So again this is a little bit more on
this. This is uh the survey regarding
where should uh if we have multifamily
being permitted in different in
different uh areas of the community by
right how should we mitigate those
instead of having a public hearing and
taking it to the board of adjustment
where they uh face uncertainty with what
that outcome is going to be. Um,
overwhelmingly of the 106 respondents on
this part of the survey, they indicate
they wanted to see increased landscape
buffers. So that would be something to
physically separate that property from
the other ones. That could be a mixture
of fences, vertical enhancements like
taller shrubs or trees, those types of
of stuff. It's not just an extra wide
lawn because that doesn't really do much
because you can just look right across
the the lawn there. Um, as you can see
there, it also talks about uh fences in
between, building setbacks, uh different
building materials to uh dress them up
and make them look a little nicer and
blend in with the community. Um, and uh
then something called a building uh
stepped setback. What that is is as a
building increases in height, the
setback increases um from the neighbors.
Uh that's very common in the planning
practice to see the ability for
uh buildings to be given more height if
they have more distance or the second
floor might be set back further. A good
example of that is in New York. Look at
the Empire State Building and it has a
step back approach. A lot of the old
historic buildings which though they're
really tall but a lot of those have
those stepbacks and stepbacks as they
developed over time. And that was for
access to light and and clean air and
circulation back in the early 1900s.
>> So um
>> through you can I ask you
>> did they bring up anything about parking
in this?
>> Yes, parking is is one uh
yes uh parking was has always been a
concern for the multif family. Um and in
this case they wanted close parking
which um bent on site and not parking
that was credits on the street or
distant.
One of the options was I don't care. I
gave this is a response we had received.
So they that's what so I said I don't
care.
Um we did receive a lot of comments on
>> girls before we move on real quick. Um
Dan Dorsch director of Habitat for
Humanity did reach out to me this
afternoon. he did want to be here
tonight because he does he was the one
who's submitted the multif family um
kind of request. Uh so he did want to be
here in support of that but have board
meeting is also tonight. Uh so he wanted
me to just let all of you know that he
would have liked to be here but because
Habitat's got their board meeting as
well he was unable to.
These are actually um numbers two,
three, four, and five uh combined. I
must left the five off of the slide.
That whole slide was left off at
council's presentation back in January.
So, if they haven't seen it, they had a
verbal um description of it. We received
a lot of landscaping comments. One of
them was just enforcement based and it
was a comment that you'll see in the
packet that was in regard to landscaping
at the senior center. Um there's a
perception that all they did was put
rock down, which they put a lot of rock
down. However, the way our landscaping
calculations are measured um and how we
do our quantities that meets the code.
Um the natural grasses and stuff that
are out there, the other areas of of
blue grass and the mature size of shrubs
and the evergreen trees, those count uh
towards your your impervious area in
your landscaped area.
So, there's uh been a little uh desire
from some of our council members to
really look at looking at how can we
prevent those rock escapes from being
put into place to really encourage more
living materials on site, whether it be
zeros escaping um and other types of
treatments that are water water-wise and
water conscious.
>> Charles, I quick follow up on that. Is
is rock landscaping like that considered
impervious or or pvious?
>> Under the current storm water fee, rock
um hardscape landscaping like that type
of stuff would be considered an
impervious material and then that would
have a required storm water fee
associated with it.
And engineering wise, I believe once you
have a rocked area or gravel area, I
think it's about an 80 to 90%
uh imperv impervabil imperousness
rating. I'm speaking as an engineer.
Yep. Getting the nod from an engineer.
Yes. So, um but you're still looking at
a surface like that that's going to
create runoff. One of the biggest
concerns with the rock landscaping is
their ability to uh really collect dirt
and dust and other things in there and
they start to breed weeds really quick
and they're not maintained. And if you
do maintain them, then you're
introducing a lot of uh pesticides and
stuff into the into the environment,
storm water, and all of that. It's just
not a a win-win.
There are questions on technical
specifications as well. This really is
not code related, but we would throw it
in here. This is how many stakes or tree
stakes you would need to plant. I think
our current specs say you need three
when you're planting a new tree. Um,
some people want to do two, but other
people want to do three. We're going to
continue to work with our forester to
make sure we get uh good information out
there, how the drip ring is constructed
around a tree, the height, the mulch,
where it is. It's all about making sure
those technical specifications are are
out there. Um I believe in this one
example uh there's actually a discussion
that they wanted to see actual soil
amendment studies for every property
that was developed. Now that can get a
little bit on the uh the detail side. I
don't know how we as staff would be able
to walk in and come in a few years later
and go, "Oh, your tree is dead. We're
going to go test your soil and it looks
like your soil is uh is the wrong
makeup, so you need to fix it. So with
the first ones, the enforcement
technical specification, we we really
haven't seen any need for changes that
involve the development regulations. It
just is that we need to continue to get
better information out.
Uh we did receive two comments that were
regarding trees. One was the same
comment we heard more recently for
street trees, just to not require street
trees or to allow for ornamental trees
instead of the canopy trees.
So,
>> can I ask a question?
>> Yes. Yes.
>> If your tree dies, do you have to
replace it? Is that what the city says?
>> Chair, members of the council,
technically, yes. Under our municipal
code, if you have a right-of-way tree um
or tree that's qualified as a street
tree, it's not able to be uh cut down or
removed um without the permission of the
city forester. And then if the city
forester has to remove a diseased or
dying tree, they have the ability to
require that land owner to put that tree
back in place. Um or they can, if they
wish, which I haven't done yet, they
could actually replace a tree at the
landowner's cost, but they've I've never
seen them do that before. Um they
usually partner with Rooted and Cheyenne
where they'll take areas where there are
tree deficiencies um and they will offer
either free trees to certain areas of
the community um or they'll have highly
reduced trees. The root in Cheyenne
program is truly an amazing one to to
get trees. I believe right now we have a
incentive area for the South Cheyenne
area. Everything south of Interstate 80
in the same limits. I think that's their
area where they can have a free street
tree put in. Um, and then that's watered
for a specific period of time by rooted
in Cheyenne till its roots get
established. It's a really good good
program.
So, we had had that one. We're not
really looking at any changes um
different from what we had seen
last year other than continuing to get
information out to the public. We just
need to make sure we can relay the
importance.
Um we are looking at doing more
community surveys to get some more
opinions from folks. There was another
comment that's around the tree um side
of things which basically said we don't
want trees to be required with any new
development or any development period.
So this is just a comparison an AI
produced photo of the blue um world
headquarters on Persian and Converse and
19th and you have trees in the upper
picture and I use this AI tool to try my
best to remove the trees and that's what
you get. You have a an area where it's
going to be a lot hotter because you're
not going to have shade in the future
when it when it grows. Um you're going
to have more storm water runoff because
you have less uh water being absorbed by
the trees. Um, again, this is this was a
comment one that we received. You know,
the community is a large community. Um,
we're not suggesting or recommending any
changes to ordinance regarding this
particular element. I should note that
Connor is probably about what a year
behind on a landscaping code update.
Talk to Dr. Rainey. Dr. Rainey's the
council sponsor on this one. I'm
exaggerating a little bit, but
we are working on a complete overhaul of
our landscaping code, uh, which is
intended to take into some of these
considerations and look at other ways
for alternatives, but it's not going to
go to the point of simply eliminating
tree planting requirements.
>> Question, what what about grass? I mean,
that's a big thing with water use.
>> And especially I hear comments about
using a different kind of grass,
especially in non-functional areas and
maybe or maybe even only allowing grass
in functional areas.
>> Yeah. So, uh through you and this is
Connor White with the planning and
development department. So, that is
something we're looking at especially
with this updated kind of landscaping
code we're looking at doing. Um, we
already have it in the UDC where we
mostly promote native seed over
basically turf. Um, we give turf lower
points than we would native seed. So,
kind of what we're looking at with um
this updated landscape code is actually
making it where you can only use turf in
functional areas. um basically
prohibiting turf grass unless it's in a
functional area and requiring native
seed um in all other areas. So that is
something that we've had discussions
about in our office. Um basically with
this landscape code amendment uh we kind
of have a group of us so it's all the
planners in our office. You've got
Jeannie Veter, our parks and greenway
planner, Mark Ellison with the forestry.
Um you have I think it's Noah Dalton I
believe is the last name but he's over
at BOPU. He's their water um kind of
conservation person that they have over
there. And then you have um Dr. Renie
from one of the council members um who's
looking to sponsor this. So you have a
group of us that are looking at it kind
of bringing trying to take all these
different ideas and things and put them
together. And that was one of the things
um that we've discussed is turf grass.
Where should it be? Should we allow it?
How much should we allow? Um and right
now it is mostly looking at just having
it in
>> muted.
>> Nope. You are not muted, Boyd.
>> Okay. I'm going to comment when you're
done.
>> Okay. Um and basically having turf grass
in those functional areas and then
um basically everywhere else that's not
considered functional would be native
seed. Um and then same thing with the
rock and everything. We're looking at
where can we just put that rock rather
than allowing it all over the site. So
there's a lot of various things we're
bouncing back and forth. It's not quite
ready to bring forward to all of you
yet. Um I have told Dr. for Renie. My my
hope is to bring that maybe in June,
which seems like a couple like a while
away, but with the way that so far these
two month first months have gone, I
don't think it's that far ahead.
>> Through you, you define what functional
area is.
>> And Mr. Chair, through you. So, we do
define it uh with this amendment. I
think we actually define it currently
right now in the UDC. I'd have to pull
that up to really explain what it is.
Um, but we do have a definition for
functional and non-functional.
Um, I can't remember if we're reworking
those specifically for this text
amendment for the landscaping, but we do
currently even in the UDC now do have
some sort of definition in our
definition section for functional and
non-functional.
I I guess just having attended the
BOPU's water summit the last couple
years there's some discussion about that
and what some cities
>> just partly
>> have done for uh water or for water
conservation the interest in limiting
turf grass and they you know like they
they don't want it in medians of roads.
They don't want it in borders around
parking lots u and in some cases not
even front yards because front yards if
in homes are typically not used like for
play areas. backyards more are used for
play areas, but then even in parks, you
know, identify the play areas versus the
non-play areas that might traditionally
have grass but uh aren't really being
used in that function. So, I think
there's a way different ways to look at
it, but that's kind of what they're
getting at. Grass is nice to have to
play on turf grass, but if you're not if
you're never going to play on it, it's
it's something you could probably live
without.
>> And then Boyd, you said you had a had
comments. Uh yes. Uh Mr. Chair, through
you. Uh I, as one might guess, I'm
probably going to land on this topic on
a in a less prescriptive attitude. Kind
of my my general perception of much of
this UDC and the commentary that we get,
responses we get is is a frustration
with being overly prescriptive. So as as
this draft is coming forward, whatever
it looks like, I I for one would really
like to have available an alternative to
language. If if the present if the
proposal is going to be prescriptive
when it comes to either banning grass or
whatever, I would like to have an option
in the draft available, a suggested
option that would be
more, I guess, permissive or
or something that would allow ultimately
allow who whomever it is that,
you know, owns the property and is
dealing with the with the actual
is dealing with the actual uh grass to
still have a choice. if they want to
have a nice turf lawn in front of their
house, maybe for market purposes or
something else, they would have that
ability. Um, as opposed to simply
banning turf for somebody that may want
it. Uh, you know, it's one thing for the
city to say, "Hey, here's what we're
going to do as a city." It's another
thing to
uh it's another thing to say and also
we're going to take away choice for
everybody else.
>> Mr. Chair through you. So just for a
clarification, the landscaping
regulations that we'd be bringing
forward are only for commercial
properties. It would not affect
residential. So our landscaping code
section doesn't actually touch
residential properties. it's anything
commercial or I guess multif family but
multif family is generally considered a
commercial development. Um but when it
comes to single family duplex town
houses we don't regulate landscaping
requirements on those. So we wouldn't
actually be banning turf grass for
residential homes. um single family um
but when it comes to commercial
properties is where they would be
limited on the ability to use turf
grass.
>> Now, I still would beg to differ on
maybe maybe we're calling uh residential
rentals commercial and not residential,
but at the end of the day, there's
people that live there. And I I I think
you know when I when I hear frustration
I hear that that the UDC is overly
prescriptive. So, you know, if we bring
something forward, I would like to have
an alternative text that
or or something that would be
be able to be offered as an alternative
that would be less prescriptive because
even a business owner is going to if
they own the property, they may they may
be
considering things that we are failing
to consider that is specific to what
they're doing. And and I think
when we take it up, and I think we're
sounds to me like we're going to take it
up. I I think it would I think we need
to
be able to be thinking about
alternatives when it, you know, when it
comes time to
propose something to the city council.
Honor, I I would also make a input into
that uh revision you're working on for
landscaping about the grass and I I
guess I I'm I'm wondering what do you
mean by uh you I think you said native
grass that would be seated rather than
sawed. Are we talking like buffalo
grass, fescue? We talking wheat grass
that's really a non-errigated grass
entirely.
I'd have to look more into how we've
defined native grasses. I know if Jeie
was here, she could probably tell you
exactly, but there are native seed
mixtures you can get. Um, it's more
prairie grasses basically. Um, that just
requires less water. Um, and even less
maintenance. Um, my understanding with
native grasses is you might only have to
mow it down to a certain height every so
often. Otherwise, it's supposed to be
left kind of a little bit taller. Um,
and then it just uses less water as
well. I believe we have definitions like
this in this new section we're working
on. Um, again, it's we've been working
on this for quite a while. It's just
other things keep popping up that we
have to that kind of put more um need
more attention than this amendment
sometimes. Um, so
some of that stuff I will note it to
make sure we do have something in there.
Um, I believe we do. Um, and then even
right now in the UDC, like I said, when
it comes to our point system, you get
more points when it comes to native seed
over turf. So with our point system,
you're required so many landscape points
with every development. Um, and the way
we have it set up, it actually pushes
people more towards native seed.
than it would uh putting in turf grass.
And then I think there is I know at
least with BOPU with certain aspects
when it comes to irrigation. I believe
it's mostly with single family though
you can get smaller taps if you have a
reduced like irrigated section of turf.
So
multiple different departments are
looking at ways to kind of res reduce
turf grass. Um
but obviously it's up to developers and
everything like that if they utilize
some of those uh things. So
>> chair members of the commission uh
Charles Bloom planning development
director again just wanted to note uh
follow up on what Connor had just
mentioned there with tap sizes. Um,
historically a single family dwelling
has had a 3/4 inch tap, which a new tap
for a single family home typically runs
about $12,000 for that tap. Uh, that's
the system development fee. That's the
the initial fee for that to go in. When
you start reducing water demand on that
property,
um, it can go down to a 5/8 inch tap,
which is $7,500 roughly. So, you're
looking at a a savings. If you go down
to Harmony Valley and off of college
down south south of high south high
school, um you'll see some properties on
smaller lots where they have
I'll call it their artificial grass
front lawns zerocaped with a Z. Um that
area over there. Uh they did that so
they could lessen their water load to
basically shave $5,000 off the
development price for those homes. So,
that's kind of a a thing we're seeing is
smaller lots limitations on what can be
watered on the property so they can get
to those smaller amounts. So, just food
for thought there.
other concerns we've heard. Um these are
ones that we've heard from folks uh
around the the community that um may
seek may give staff a little bit of
direction to move forward on these. Uh
there's one that's not on the list um
that's kind of jumped up more recently
as a result of the Y fresh farms
discussion with the annexation which our
representatives here on that as well um
which we haven't added to the list yet
but it's uh probably going to be
something that will be discussed at the
end um as you all come together here at
the end for this. But we've seen one
which is kind of revisiting the carports
and front yards. Uh we did have a
exercise a few years ago where we
started to look at uh carports in the
front yards and we had proposed that
they had some type of design standards
and essentially there was no appetite
from the governing body to move forward
with carports
but appears now that that appetite has
once risen again. Um this typically
follows large hail events where people
are like why don't we allow carports in
the front yards. Well right now they're
classified as accessory structures. just
they're not supposed to be in the front
yard. They have to meet setbacks from
the from the front property line or the
side property line. We're not going to
talk about where this example is because
there's a whole slew of issues with it
because not only does it meet setbacks,
it's also constructed in the right of
way. So, it's it's there. Um, so we do
have believe a council member who is
looking at um seeing if there's council
desire to start allowing these as their
own use with some simple standards which
would mean that they would have to have
at least certain sites open because once
you start closing these off they start
to uh attract
other things, tools, boxes, things. So
they start to to really
uh stack up. So, there are a lot of
these exist in the community and you can
go buy this at any local um hardware
store. No questions asked. Even though
90% of the time the application's not
going to be legal. It's just like that's
just like buying illegal lighting at
Menards. You can do it any day you wish.
Um parking minimums for non-residential
uses. This is one that we keep on
bringing up. Um, we do see this popping
up in a lot of neighboring states where
they're getting a top- down approach
from the state legislature,
um, where it says, "We don't want the
cities to be able to tell people how
much parking they have or they have to
provide." Uh, this area right here, this
is uh, blue sweetgrass. Bluegrass.
>> Blueass.
>> Bluegrass. I I've lived here for I've
been in this area for over 20 years. I
still can't tell those two streets
apart. bluegrass, sweet grass. Um, but
here we have a a tale of two parking
lots. You have Texas Roadhouse, which is
located on the bottom left, where they
actually wanted to provide additional
parking, which exceeded our parking
requirements, and they built that
overflow lot to the to the west. Um,
they had to do a parking study to
justify that they could support that
that parking so they weren't building
too much. They developed through a
floodway. They had to go through the
Army Corps of Engineers, lots of
engineering. It wasn't a cheap project,
but it worked for them. Meanwhile, we
have a another property kind of on the
northwest part. You'll see the white
roofed building, which is the Advanced
Auto Parts and I believe the Where is
the No, it's a hot tub place, the
Advanced Auto Parts.
There's another building to the south
with a small parking lot where they
wanted to put a business in there and
they wanted to remove a parking space
for like a storage building that would
go on the lot. Well, that ran in its own
hiccups because they couldn't take away
their parking. So, the thing with these
properties is they both are like, well,
our business model will work with the
parking that we want to have. So, where
why are we the ones telling people how
many parking spaces they need where
ultimately it's going to come down to
what their comfort level is for their
business and also it's going to come
down to what their lender or financer
feels is appropriate. Usually, it's the
lender or financer that determines the
parking. So, with that being said, we're
really striving to remove the minimum
requirements for parking so we can let
it be dependent on the developer, but we
still want to make sure that we keep the
balances in check that we're not getting
excessive amounts of parking, which I
don't think we have that problem as much
anymore. that used to be planned for the
day after Thanksgiving for Black Friday
and that's what people plan for. I think
those days are still there but it's not
near as important anymore.
Of course, with uh the residential um
uses, multif family, apartments, town
homes, we're not proposing those. Those
all need to stand on their own within
the current parking requirements. Um
right now for a multif family it's
uh for onebedroom in our efficiencies
it's 75 per unit is one oh it's one
sorry one space per unit.
>> Oh anyway so it that seems to be be
working uh pretty well right now. more
recent changes to parking just to
decrease it just a little bit to um for
multif family um seem to open the
floodgates for a lot of multif family
development because number one they're
confident that their model um and their
proformer will work to support limited
parking you have developments out at uh
Saddle Ridge you have the development
downtown you have developments on US30
and you have the developments uh north
of Del Range that are all using that new
parking model and they've said nothing
but compliments on
So, it seems to me like like in your
lower photograph, it seems to me like
the risk is if you let businesses kind
of decide for themselves, my thought is
they would probably tend toward not
building any more parking than they
absolutely thought they'd need. And if
they need more, they're not going to
care too much. And they'll either that
will either cause more on street parking
or even people parking in neighboring
parking lots that aren't associated with
the business, which probably won't be
optimal either.
>> Is it's all it's good observations. Um I
don't know where the entirety of the
council feels here. It seems like in the
past the council has
well mo a majority of the council had
not supported any changes. Um in
Colorado cities can't regulate parking
requirements anymore in Utah. Um I
believe that's recently approved in Utah
as well and it's on the radar in Montana
as well. So it's it's a national trend
that's that's popping up. All those
things you you talk about. Yes, it it
does pose issues. people have a very
healthy relationship with their vehicle
which is very expensive. Um, and
if parking becomes inconvenient, it can
necessitate change and people can slowly
change and start looking at alternative
modes to get from point A to point B.
You never know. We imagine if parking
was required when downtown started. It
look different down here.
This is a fun This is a fun one. Um,
this is actually in the works right now
and it's been legal added. A portion of
this has to move forward to your next
planning commission meeting. Although,
fair warning, it may be postponed
because I have not completed the final
draft yet. It's just on the agenda as a
placeholder with a legal ad in case we
miraculously can get it finished. And
that's the historic horse racing
facilities. Um, so what we're looking at
is a three-pronged approach to to these.
Uh, this is amending our current special
use process, which is one that you have
never really seen in whole. The board of
adjustment has seen it in part. We have
a special use process which is set up
for uh oil and gas exploration
activities. Right now, out of HR Ranch,
we had exploration activity and that's
the noisy part where they're drilling.
They're going with their horizontal
lines. They're trying they're doing
their exploration for oil and gas and in
lots of communities you see the large
sound walls that are put up for that
use. So that's something that goes
through our special use process right
now. It's uh
worded,
for lack of a better term, poorly. Um it
doesn't fit the current unified
development code and it needs a complete
overhaul. Um these are usually
politically charged decisions um that
have a lot of politics behind them. So
instead of putting the planning
commission um or the board of adjustment
on the hot seat, especially the board of
adjustment, we don't want them to have
to make um decisions that are
politically charged. Uh we pass the buck
on to the governing body. So what we're
looking at doing is uh amendments to the
historic horse racing um allowances to
do a couple of things. Number one,
identify uh development standards for
new ones that are developed or ones that
are significantly enhanced or enlarged
with separations from schools, churches,
childc carees, the typical uh uses of
land that you would see separation from
um adult activities or gambling
facilities uh from. We're also looking
at establishing a receiving zone or an
overlay district uh which would say
these are uses these are areas of the
community where you can establish these
and you don't have to go through a
special use permit process. So trying to
dangle a carrot out there saying hey um
if you're going to go in this location
you're going to get your approval a
little bit quicker and it's going to be
less politically charged. Um so that's
coming. Um, I'm optimistic we can get it
to you on your full agenda for March.
Um, but it might be looking like
we'll see. We'll check. Um, I think it
would be a March 16th date. It wouldn't
land on St. Patrick's Day. Thank
goodness.
Uh, sexually oriented businesses. Uh
this is this is one that we haven't
touched in decades and I don't know if
any of you all have ever read the
regulations but if you dive into
municipal code
they have not been updated in forever.
They should have been wrapped into the
unified development code with
development standards. We're looking
just to to modify and up update that
because you never know when we're going
to have someone that moves in that needs
a license. Right now we don't have any
license establishments.
Um we like this is the old Cupid's
bookstore that some may remember
downtown. Now it's occupied by the
Denine um townhouse development that was
demolished and put there. That was an
old uh video and magazine store. Um that
would have had to register as sexually
oriented business. the green door um
that would have had to register.
However, it was a pre-existing use, so
it never had to register. So, what we're
doing two tier is special uses and HHRs.
Those are going to be done together.
Then, we're going to follow up after
working with our city clerk to bring
what's nicknamed so um those are going
to be uh brought in the unified
development code a little bit. They'll
follow that later. um they're a lower
priority. Um but I feel like whenever we
think about something, oh that's not
going to happen two weeks later I'm like
seriously that's going to happen. So it
it happens.
Any questions on that?
The HHR and special use one has about
five different prongs that we'll be
looking at. It's a pretty pretty large
one that needs all of its um eyes
dotted and T's crossed and even the
lowercase J's need their dots. Yeah, I
read articles about the legislature and
in past months about the committees in
the legislature considering the gambling
things and whether there should be more
uh local input and local control over
placement of gambling facilities and and
one hand I think there's a contingent
that says well cities and towns can
handle that through their zoning
regulations
or zoning ordinances and then on the
other hand they they think you know the
governing body should kind of have a
more unil or more broad-based ability to
approve or deny those on a case- by case
basis. But it um I kind of I kind of was
curious about why they weren't addressed
as much it seems like in the zoning.
>> Yes. Uh chair through to the commission.
Right now they are in every district
except for downtown uh central business
district. They are conditional use
approval requirements, which they go on
to the board of adjustment for approval,
which it's been really surprising that
the board of adjustment has not had to
face an angry mob of folks. I'm shocked.
Um, they've pretty much been quiet. Um,
and we've had a lot of these uses that
have gone through. Um, and we've
conditioned them to kind of enhance at
least the physical characteristics of
the site. you know, we've introduced a
new use into the the community. Um, this
will stay on the lookout. Uh, we're
going to hopefully have a a draft ready
for public review soon and then we're
going to see how we're going to move
forward. But we have a placeholder on
that March um agenda for the planning
commission.
All right, we have uh four and five. And
the parking lot surfacing and
payceptions one actually has taken a
little bit of a a change um and gotten a
higher priority more recently. Um right
now we have a lot of uses where
they don't use the parking that they
have all the time like less than one or
two days a week like a a place of
worship, place of assembly. They might
have overflow parking for Easter,
Christmas where that might not be
necessary to have pavement there year
round. So, we're looking at ways like
items like churches won't have to pave
their parking lots. We're also looking
at uh some of our rural character uh
park um trail head and park facilities.
For example, East Park at on Persian
that's was developed in the county. it
didn't need to have uh paving
requirements and the only paving
requirement that's out there is for ADA
access which is the concrete parking
space you see for ADA that connects to
the trail head. Um other areas that
we've that has kind of heightened the
importance of this um is moving it up um
and that's due to agricultural zoning.
right now if you have a use in the
agricultural district
um technically you'd have the paving
requirement um so we'd want to make sure
there's a easier option to not allow or
not require that paving again with any
new parking lot it's federal it's a
federal requirements city county
wherever you're at that if you're
putting a new parking lot in you need to
have an ADA parking space you know
that's your first that's your only paid
space that you're required to have under
the federal ADA standards if you have
customers that come to your site. So,
we're making sure that that's going to
be um put together that has gained more
importance uh with several agricultural
uses that have been identified, you
know, with the latest annexation. And I
should note that none of this would be
retroactive making anybody comply with
anything because everything that's
brought is being brought in at this.
It seemed it seems like I recall when I
was on the board of adjustment, there
was a campground out east, maybe KOA.
They wanted they proposed maybe an
expansion but without paving the
roadways, the internal roadway network.
>> Chair three to members of the
commission. Yes, that's correct. That
was the campground on just south of
Venture Drive um east of Camp Stool Road
over there. they wanted to expand and
they wanted to keep their aisles and
everything gravel. Um they applied for a
variance to try to keep the gravel um
drive aisles. I believe that variance
was denied and they ultimately came and
ended up having to pave their drive
aisles. We brought that up to the to the
de uh to the planning commission and the
city council a couple of years ago at
one of these annual review updates and
the message from the council was clear
that we wanted at least the drive aisles
paved for those facilities.
So, they even um had come to the someone
had even mentioned that they wanted to
see drive aisles and like storage yards
paved. And that one's a little bit
harder to to enforce when storage yards
could be more of a free-for-all. So, we
we don't enforce that for a storage
yard.
>> And actually, with the new campground
regulations that did get adopted by the
governing body, we do require drive
aisles to be paved.
>> Oh, yeah. I can prove about that. So, we
did actually have that in there uh with
those new campground regulations which
were adopted by the governing body. They
are in the updated UDC.
>> Here's another one that has recently
popped up. Uh we don't have a mechanism
in place for long-term temporary
construction uses. Um here you're
looking at two different items. That's
uh what's the referred to as trailer
town out the meta complex which is where
all their offices are. Um, sometimes it
moves around a little bit. There's lots
of lighting and stuff like that. And
then this one here is a temporary use
that lasted for a few years outside of
the hospital. You see the governor's
mansion in the background. We don't have
standards to let those last for more
than their six-month um period. So,
we're looking at adding a temporary
construction uses, which is a section
which will do some simple things as
define what you can and can't do, what
surfacing looks like, reclamation
standards for afterwards, how does this
go, simple site plan preparation so we
know where fire access is, and probably
the most important thing is uh lighting.
Uh we have a large temporary
construction facility out east of town
on Venture with a lot of stray light. if
you will, and we're having trouble
finding tools to address this interim
period. So, it's um kind of risen as a
important item to add to our list of
items to move forward.
Here's one from the planning commission
that we received. Um this one we I
believe had last year. This is a block
length exceptions. It seems to be
something that pops up quite frequently.
In fact, we just approved a
committee. They just recommended
approval of a subdivision off of Melton
and Powder House with a block length
exception that you all saw just at your
last meeting. Um, so this is one that
we're continuing to look at ways to
better define. Um, I don't know if the
planning commission has any feedback for
us as we try to figure out the path
forward on this or if y'all wish to even
have a subcommittee you can establish on
your own if you really feel like, you
know, rolling up your sleeves and
getting involved. I wouldn't um have a
problem with with that.
So, we'd like some guidance from you all
on how this would work. Yeah, I don't
know exactly how it should work, but I
know our concern was on those two larger
apartment complexes north of Walmart
that u I mean they've got their own
internal parking, their own internal
roadways, etc. for their residents. But
we were concerned that they were taking
up such large pieces of land that
especially if there was adjacent develop
like maybe single family neighborhoods
north of there that that it would be
very restrictive for pedestrians to be
able to pass through those areas without
having to go a long way around. Um not
so much we weren't so much concerned
about vehicles because they don't take
that long to go around anyway. that
pedestrian access. It seems like that's
kind of a primary driver of block length
requirements or block size requirements
anyway. And uh so that was what we were
concerned about. And then you know
obviously we heard from the owners that
they're I think they have concerns about
being able to control who's in those
complexes to some extent and u being
able to you know if there's a public
rightway through there can they control
who's in there? if people are using
those for purposes they'd rather not. Um
so I I can see both sides of it. It's
comp complex issue.
>> Yes. And chair three to the commission
and with that um concern we've we tried
to figure out like what is the best time
frame for acquiring these connections
especially in the section 20 area where
we have a lot of large tracks of land
that are developing with a very
uncertain
future nearby. We do have what's called
a a transportation network plan, which
which you will see with preliminary
plats, but that's a general overview
saying this is where your collector
streets will be. This will be where your
minor arterials are. It doesn't get down
the nitty-gritty of what's going to
happen on the other side of my property
boundary.
Um, so we're trying to figure out how do
we how do we make that work and how do
we make it so someone's not having to
overengineer their concept plan at the
concept level when they're just trying
to see if they can get their approvals
to take those next steps forward when
they have to really dive in and do their
full engineering. Um, it's that it's the
chicken and the egg type of of question.
So what ended up happening with the last
not the last one but the one on the
north side of Carlson here is that one
turned into a condition on the plat that
it had to essentially say
you need to provide this connection to
the satisfaction of staff with the site
plan which then you got to trust in
staff. I can let you know that's going
to be a better connection than what you
have at the Walmart. There's a couple of
turns that could have been avoided, but
we got a pretty sharp crew that's able
to identify what's good and what's not
not great. Um, Wasatch has indicated
that they do intend to provide
pedestrian connections to the west as
the ger develops next to Sam's Club is
that grocery store that's proposed over
there. So, they're looking at that
connection.
>> Mr. chair through you. Um, in thinking
about brainstorming this and and what
something could look like coming
forward, I I know we've got our
transportation network plan. Is there
any way to designate or call out
pedestrian transportation as as part of
a transportation network and and not
necessarily only being adjacent to
streets? that would allow us to tackle,
you know, whether you know what you can
do to,
you know, get your block block size
exception.
Would that be a way to get to
kind of the end result that we're
looking for? If we're if we're going to
focus on at least making sure
pedestrians can get around even if
people have to drive their car the long
way around.
fair members of the commission. I I
think there that's a a really good
discussion point that you have there. Um
I do like that. I do like that idea and
I think that
you and I could discuss that a little
bit more about how that would look
because it could be a
possibly just throwing a term out there
like a a block length exception,
you know, mitigation plan for lack of a
better term. So, you know, we understand
our block lengths are gone, but this is
what we're going to do. And I
immediately jump into like the vision of
a Lynchian diagram, which is like you
have arrows showing this is where your
pedestrian connections are going to be,
you know, through this area. It's going
to generally pass through your lot to go
this direction. I think that could be
something worth exploring that wouldn't
take too many words.
All right, hearing nothing else on that,
I'll move on to our next three items,
which are all staff staff ones. Uh, one
is just our zoning enforcement process,
and this is one that's been actively in
the works. I feel like we just updated
our zoning um enforcement process. We
still got to do it again. Um, right now
our
violations are criminal violations. So,
you technically could serve jail time
for offense that's too tall. Um, that's
not the way it is supposed to be. Um, so
we want to make it a a civil offense.
So, we're looking at changes there. So,
it' be a a civil offense. It changes the
uh court in which it would go to. Um,
these are just two examples of of zoning
enforcements that we would see. The
first one's a tall fence in a front
yard. The second one is someone's
driving that vehicle. No, I'm just
kidding. It's the lighting that you see
shining into the front yard of a house.
We see a lot of um, lighting violations.
So, this is something that I believe
Connor um, and Seth have both been
spearheading. Um, it's
trying to move forward, but there's a
lot of other projects that are that
leaprog this one. Um, so this one, we
can't promise you it'll come through,
but we're hoping that it'll gain
traction um, hopefully by the end of the
year.
>> And with this one, I should also note
Seth has been looking into all sections
of code that would have to be changed,
including municipal. And I think he's at
like a 50page ordinance already um, for
this because it there's a lot of codes
that have to be changed from criminal to
civil. Most of the time with these, they
don't make it that far. So, it's not
like every zoning violation is becoming
a criminal offense.
Usually with zoning violations, people
come into compliance before we get to
that point. Um, so we haven't gone to
that extent of criminally charging
anybody for a zoning violation. Um but
right now that is how it reads and it
could be taken that way but staff
doesn't feel that it should be taken
that direction. So that has been looked
into but again this it's a big kind of
change than just zoning code. We have to
change it in also municipal code and
there's a lot of sections. So,
>> and and I can confidently say that never
have we had a zoning enforcement action
that's ended in jail time,
nor do we anticipate that ever to occur.
So, now I said that, I'll be like, what?
No, I'm just kidding. No, number one is
just because of the sheer amount of time
that it takes for a zoning enforcement
process. uh you have 30-day notice right
off the get-go, another 21-day notice,
then you have to be able to um find time
with the attorneys that if they have
time to process that. And it it can take
forever. It does take a long time.
So, our second on our wish list, which I
I think we're going to do it this year,
this is good, is lot types. Um, for
those of you who haven't uh dug around
in um article 5 of our code, I'm sure
you all have. We have lot types that are
you hear planner spit off all the time
like DD1, AD1s, CD2s, DD7s,
MU, whatevers, all of that. That's not
very common out here in the
in the West. um this this lot type idea
and the regulations that came into
effect really were born out of the
authors of the unified development code
back in 2012. Um it was something that
they did. It was like a form-based code
type of thing. So they they did it. Um,
what's more simple is what you see on
the left, which that's a very, very
abbreviated simple version, is what we
used to have here, which says if you
have a R1 zone lot, you're going to have
to be 20 ft from your front, 5 ft from
each side, 10 ft from your back, and
you're and that's almost what it is. Uh,
so it's it's looking to streamline it.
we've had a lot of and make the
conversation easier and it deletes about
40 pages of our development regulations
because those are we have tons of law
types in there. So, it's a goal. Um we
have traction, we have uh council
support. Um and every time we sort of
start to draft this things change,
especially when it comes to lot sizes
and multifamily permissibility,
that these all have to work together.
So changing this, by the way, we also
need to be cognizant of how our
landscaping regulations
and uh percent covers landscape area are
stated there because they're heavily
dependent on lot types right now.
Now, who's ever turned to the back of
the UDC
article 7? Raise your hands or or make
yourself known online if you turn to
article 7.
Line it. Okay, perfect. So, uh, council
member or commissioner Olsen, sorry.
What did you do when you saw article 7?
>> Uh, chair for you, I honestly wondered
about the applicability in the community
of Cheyenne.
I've never seen form-based codes
applied. I know we've seen it in other
communities, but
in Cheyenne, I don't
have any clue of where it would be or
how it would be applied. So, yeah.
>> Yeah. And article 7 is our formbbased
codes for it's it is uh definitely one
for the scholar. Um it's not one that
would best be applied here in Cheyenne.
It's never been used since 2012.
It hasn't had the updates to the use
table that we've done in the past. Um,
anyone could walk in and try to use the
formbbased code of him wanted to right
now. Um, but it is a very tedious
process with lots of approvals, lots of
public involvement, and it just doesn't
really work well for the city of
Cheyenne. So, our goal is to delete it
and everything that it relates to, which
it has a huge trickle down effect in our
our code. I challenge any one of you to
read the formbbased code article and
just see if you think it's a it's
wonderful. So that's on our wish list.
We we think we can get it deleted. We do
have a staff member who is tasked with
identifying all of the connected pieces
um so we can see what we're getting
ourselves into so we can start to move
forward on that. Um but that'll be great
to take out.
Th this is totally different than plan
unit developments.
>> Chair through you. It is 100% different.
It talks about uh different types of
transexs which uh commissioner Wigum may
recognize from uh school and education
talking about transexs.
uh lots of different
regulations clearly based on on form and
what's uh called regulating plans which
are like plania developments but even
more so because they get down to your
actual design of your house and your
bulk what your house looks like its
context how it looks compared to the
neighboring house it I couldn't imagine
it
Mr. Chair, it's for you. Um, did you say
it was used though in 2012? Like it came
up or what was that comment about?
>> Chair three to Commissioner Hernandez.
Um, it was implemented in 2012. It was
it was first introduced in 2012 with the
new unified development code and it
hasn't been touched since then. Like
hasn't been touched at all.
>> Chair through you on that one. I just a
question for uh director Bloom. Aren't
these typ more typical in larger
communities? Say like metropolitan areas
or like areas like Denver or Salt Lake
City for example.
>> J3 to Commissioner Olsen. Yes, they're
very common in in very dense
communities, heavily urbanized
communities,
ones that that China doesn't really fall
into. Um you would see something like
this in
I would Denver has some form-based codes
um and some form-based zone districts. I
believe San Francisco does. Uh some
areas of um
probably Seattle in that area do, but
you'll see it in those much more larger
urban environments than you would see in
the rural environments.
All right, with that, that's all we have
on our our update. Um, we do always open
this up for public comment. If the
public wants to mention or comment,
they're more than welcome to to do that.
And then in the end what we ask for is
for you to follow our rec our
recommendation in the staff report which
is to acknowledge receipt of the annual
report. Um but if there's something you
all really really really want us to do
or prioritize um under the unified
development code the very beginning you
all are able to oh it's in the memo.
you're able to direct us to do that as
the planning commission.
>> I I had one more question because I'd
gone through the package you guys sent
out and you had a long example in there
of a of a request to the board of
adjustment uh for the multifamily
housing I think on 12th Street and it
was denied uh according to the te to the
narrative. Uh, I wondered what was the
reason that the board of adjustment
denied that
uh request.
>> Mr. Chair, through you. I'm trying to
remember off the top of my head because
I wasn't actually at that meeting. Um,
and I don't know if we have any planners
here that were um I believe there were
neighbors that just came out against it.
I don't remember exactly why the board
ended up denying it. Um, it probably had
to do with just neighbors not wanting
it. Although, the board did approve
another multif family about two blocks
to the west of this one. So, it's a
little kind of contradicting with how
they made that decision. Um, but
that's my understanding is staff was
recommending approval. Um, but there
were some neighbors that came out in
protest
and the board chose to deny that multif
family request and I believe the request
was for four units on the property split
into two separate buildings. So, you had
a duplex in the front and then behind it
was another duplex and then the parking
was off the alley. Um, is what I believe
was proposed.
So, I don't know the specifics on
exactly why they chose to deny that one.
Um, but my understanding is there was
protest from neighbors and ultimately
the board chose to deny it.
>> Yeah, I I think there's probably some of
those criteria that talk about
compatibility with the neighborhood and
that's kind of a seems to me a little
bit of a subjective one that they can
usually use to to deny something,
especially if there's a lot of
opposition in the neighborhood.
And chair, with that being the
conclusion of our items, I respectfully
ask that you could ask if there's any
public comment.
Okay, we'll do that now. Uh if you have
public comment, please come up come up
to the podium and give your name and uh
make your comment.
Hi. Uh, my name is Chelsea McCort. Um, I
live on Bent around the corner. Um, and
I apologize to Mr. Bloom and Mr. Connor.
They're probably tired of seeing my face
today. Um, but that's okay. Um, so I was
here last time you guys had a meeting.
Um, and I spoke and you mentioned coming
back and speaking um, about the same
topic would be beneficial perhaps in
this particular setting. And so I um
wanted to talk on two interconnected um
issues that I kind of see as I was
looking at the the UDC itself. Um and
and maybe am I able to ask a question?
>> Yeah,
>> I think that'd be appropriate. Sure.
>> Okay. Um I I was curious why does the
UDC use the A zoning for the dual
purpose of of land being held and also
for like an actual a use.
>> So Mr. Chair through you. So with a
zoning um
basically when it comes to a yes it has
agricultural uses. We've used it as a
holding zone because that zone is a
little bit easier to reszone. Um it's
probably the lowest intense use zone
that we have.
Um, so to reszone something from a to
another zone district is easier than if
we just threw it into the MR zone and
then say somebody wanted to change that
to light industrial. Um,
might not be the best example, but with
agg um it's just the least intense z uh
it's usually used for an agricultural
use. agricultural uses. Uh, for example,
everything behind Walmart, we propose
that whole area bezoned a because they
are doing grazing out there. But that
will allow it to as it redevelops to
reszone it a little bit easier than
giving it just a straightup zone that
has restrictions already. Uh, when it
comes to if we gave it MR and they
wanted to do high density residential,
well, now they need to go through a
bunch of other processes. um
or if they went to MUB for mixed use
business. It's a little bit different
when you're trying to give it kind of
these more in high high intense zone
districts. Um
that's how it's been at least since I've
been here. We've always just had the a
zone be kind of that holding zone. It
does allow for agricultural uses though
because it is an a zone. Um, but just
because we give a property the egg zone
doesn't necessarily mean it has to be a
holding zone for that property. It just
has been used as one by other developers
because that's how it's written. If it
is given a because it allows for
agricultural uses, those usually have
um
certain
state rules and regulations around the
egg uses where we don't require fees at
platting which we have now changed. So
that no longer matters. So you might
actually see less properties coming in
or large developments coming in and them
zoning properties agg so that they
wouldn't have to pay their fees because
now fees are due a building permit. But
in the past that's what people use the a
zone for is it got them out of having to
pay park fees. So it was considered a
holding zone for that because they
didn't know what the development was
going to be. They didn't want to give it
a zone district and pay fees when they
didn't know how it was going to develop.
Um so that's basically what that's why
we have a the way it is. Um it has
agricultural uses but yes it has been
used as a holding zone because we didn't
charge fees uh at the time of platting.
>> Yeah I remember back the um infamous
10acre uh parcel off of Ridge Road that
kind of started the whole idea of this
baseline zoning upon annexation. uh was
originally proposed with the annexation
to have an NR3 zone and then the
governing body approved the annexation
but not the zoning and then so I think a
couple months later they changed or they
did zone it as AG and of course
subsequently the developer came in with
a request for what NR2 zoning which did
get approved so it's zoned that now
>> and chair members of the of the
commission Connor did did speak to a
very important point is it primarily
took took on the role of a holding zone
because of fees that were associated for
parks. um the impact fees for parks and
public safety that are required um at
the time of platting because almost
always a land that's brought in is
platted um and then there'd be a fee
deal if it was anything other than a so
when you had a let's just use an example
of say Bison Business Park for example
that's coming in large data center
development that's step one in a huge
development where they're annexing 1,000
acres where there is A there was back
then an extraordinary fee that would go
with that development at the very very
tip of the development process. So it
was to ensure confidence in the
developer. Same thing we look at
sweetgrass. There's a lot of a zone um
sweetgrass as well that's outside that
general pud because they didn't want to
pay those fees that day. Now there
is probably an argument to change that
um because we've changed the way the
fees are collected recently and this is
something we hadn't thought about is the
fees have been changed that they're due
at the building permit not at the
annexation or planning action. So
investigating an alternative
uh statement for the a zone could be
considered appropriate. It could be
something that we could throw onto our
work plan to see if calling it a holding
zone is accurate right now because we
have an annexation that was filed
recently and
you know a lot of it's not all
annexations are going to automatically
be zoned a anymore because we have our
uh p our basically our
what do we call it our assigned zoning
sorry I had a brain brain slip there our
our assigned zoning which comes in place
that's not necessary act. We can look at
that.
>> Does uh does the zoning have something
directly to do with the property tax
assessment or does the assessor assess
the land use kind of independently from
the zoning?
>> Chair members of the commission. I'm not
exactly certain with how their metrics
work for everything. Um, zoning is a
small piece of the puzzle for the
assessor, but when it comes to
agricultural uses,
there is a the ability to have a reduced
assessment if you meet specific criteria
of the county assessor. For example, I
know that when the section 20
properties, which is the coal properties
uh north of Frontier Mall,
they have the agricultural exemption
based on their use of the land and
proceeds that come from the agricultural
use. And that's one of the heavier
factors. Um, but regarding how much the
zoning um plays a part in it, I'm sure
it's it's some um but I I don't know the
exact certainty of how how the
assessment business works.
>> Excellent. No, thank you. I appreciate
that and thank you guys for the the
response there. Um, I guess that kind of
plays into then, uh, something that that
I think that might be
good for the city moving forward would
be to look at possibly um, creating a
separate definition for some form of
holding zone. Um, as discussed, a lot of
the fees associated with are pretty
mitigated at this point. Um, I think
it's it's problematic, especially as the
city continues to expand and butt up
more against um urban and rural uh
things on the outskirts of the city
county lands. Um, I also think that that
while it's not a significant problem, I
think there is kind of a um inherent
assumption that if you see an a zone in
some cases that that is intended for
some form of future development just
because they're one and the same. And so
it may unconsciously create this
association that lands that are agg that
are truly a zones may also be seen kind
of as secondary potential future
development if the land were obtained at
some point. Um all in all though I I
just think that that would be beneficial
which also kind of plays into the
secondary point that I wish to make was
that um again as we're incorporating
more and more uh rural lands lands that
are doing a lot more farming um lands
are doing smallcale commercial farming
uh that looking into incorporating some
form of um urban agricultural definition
into the zone. I do know that Mr. Bloom
has been working on that at least in
part regarding to the whole wresh parcel
annexation. Um but I just wish to speak
about the again reemphasizing the
purpose of that that it has um a lot of
potential to benefit the future of
zoning within Cheyenne. So I I thank you
for the time. Any questions?
>> Any questions from the commission?
>> Any more to add by the staff on this
general issue?
>> M the commission? No, there's nothing
further to add.
>> Okay, thank you very much.
>> Thank you.
Hi, I'm Tommy Nicely with YFresh and I
just wanted to also go down on record
that we would like to support some urban
a definitions
um get some laws and ordinances in place
for protection and then just offer
um something to look into. I know you
guys were talking about the whole
limiting turf. Um, looking into soil
food web and getting the biology added
um really does help with water holding
capacities
and may be a solution for or an option.
Um, be something to look into. Oh, thank
you.
>> Thank you. Any questions from the
commission for Miss Nicely?
Okay. Thank you.
and chair, members of the commission, I
apologize I didn't mention this earlier,
but uh Miss Nicer reminded me that
through the discussions with the latest
annexation action, we have been working
on creating an urban farm definition um
which would also result in some heavier
discussion on urban agricultural
operations and creating an ordinance
that would drop into the unified
development code to that effect. So,
that's something that has evolved before
this PowerPoint was made and finalized
or since since that's happened. So, uh
we're working on getting that put
together in our code. We have talked
with county planning as well. Um they've
identified that there are several other
agricultural uses in um areas near the
corporate limits of the city. So this
would be a beneficial change not only
for uh this one property owner, this
another property owner doing
agricultural use as well in in this
county pocket annexation but also other
ones that may come in the future.
Okay, thank you. Any more public
comments?
You went online? Nope. Okay, public
comments closed. Going once, going
twice, three times, and public comment
is closed.
So what do do we just going to
acknowledge receipt of the report or
what what do we what do you need from
us? Chair three to the commission. Um I
think it'd be appropriate to acknowledge
receipt of the report that was presented
but also acknowledge the comments that
were made by um Miss McCort and by Miss
Nicely. Um, and then if you wish for us
to proceed, uh, a little bit more
quickly with certain items, uh, please
let us know. Um, but with the
agricultural items that were mentioned,
I would include in any motion. Good luck
putting this together. I'm sure you
someone will. Um I would say that I
would at least include
um a direction for staff to move forward
with the agricultural based um
amendments that were mentioned today. So
that puts our feet to the fire a little
bit.
Uh,
>> you got something, boy?
>> It's just that the noise in the
background got loud enough I didn't
think you'd be able to hear it. just so
um my feedback my feedback on this
agricultural issue as we're kind of
contemplating whether to accelerate it
or not as we acknowledge receipt is
in my mind I am not I'm not bothered by
the notion of of agricultural
the zoning being a holding zone because
in my mind an agricultural use or
designation should be broadly permissive
to allow any and every kind of
agriculture that that one would expect
in an area that is is not developed. Um,
if we're if we're going to start
ratcheting down what kind of agriculture
somebody does in an agricultural zone or
having different designations of
agriculture,
I I don't think I like that because
again, as I mentioned earlier, it
strikes me as something that would be
moving in a direction of becoming overly
prescriptive
when, you know, part of what makes
Cheyenne distinct is is we are generally
surrounded by rural areas that are
appropriate for anything from raising
plants to raising animals. So, you know,
I I get the discomfort of of an
implication being that if something's
zoned agricultural, then that means it's
being held open for zoning.
But I I don't know that we need to have
another holding zone that has more
limitations on it than agricultural use
that would exclude agricultural uses
until it gets developed. I kind of like
the idea of of,
you know, as you're looking at it and
looking at it broadly, I I don't know
that I would want to accelerate it. If
if it comes forward, fine. I just don't
want to have this have an unintended
consequence of of trying to accelerate
multiple definitions of agricultural
uses
result in
more restrictive zoning when my sense is
that is not the goal.
>> I would tend to agree with Boyd. don't I
also don't have a problem with
continuing to use it as a holding zone
though I can understand the concern
about the connotation that might give to
people. Um I remember that you know with
the 10 acre parcel there on Ridge Road
that I mentioned earlier there was there
was kind of a bit of a panic there for a
while because it was sort of no man's
land. I mean if there's no zoning
district assigned to a piece of land
that is within the city that what do you
do with it or what can be done or can't
be done on that piece of land. So, I
think it has to be something. Unless we
create a whole new zoning district that
might be similar to a but not exactly. I
I don't necessarily see the benefit of
going to the trouble to do that.
I guess in terms of priorities, um,
looking back over my notes, I I think a
priority uh for me would be pursuing the
uh the first item with the multifamily
being more of a permitted use in zoning
districts. Um,
because I think that that ties in with a
concern that the city's had for some
time about trying to uh increase
affordable housing and attainable
housing.
Mr. Chair, through you I would echo echo
those comments about uh prioritizing. I
think in my mind the things that we need
to prioritize are the things that
en enable our urban areas to more align
with what people would expect an urban
area to to do. um multif multifamily
housing kind of moving toward density
and trying and and the other one that I
guess is a priority to me based on
what's happening in the area north of
Frontier Mall and Walmart is to
really delve in on on how we can do a
better job of protecting
future devel protecting pedestrians
ability to be pedestrians
as as our city builds out. So, those are
kind of the two top issues to me in my
mind.
>> Any more comments from the commission?
>> Mr. Chair, through you. Um, I have a
little concern about some parking. I um
when you're considering parking for
businesses, do you consider that they
need to make allowance for their
employees or not? or is it just looking
at
the
person coming in to buy something?
>> So, Mr. Chair through you, it depends on
the use.
>> So, in um our use table, there are some
uses that we require certain parking for
employees versus
um
customers. And then in other cases, so
like general office, you're just
required a certain number of spaces
based on the square footage of the
building. Well, there's there's a
general office complex that's at kind of
on the corner of uh Yellowstone and uh
Vanderhigh. It's kind of behind the M
Mustang uh service station and on to one
side. You drive into that thing, there's
no problem, but when you try to leave
leave, you're taking your life into your
hands because it appears that all of the
employees are parked on the street all
around that thing. It's dangerous when
you try to leave that thing either on on
Vanderhigh or even on a side street
behind. I can't remember the name of
that street, but it is th those that's
that street and the one to the I think
it would be to the north. I'm not
certain. the two streets that are the
not not the busy streets, they're just
loaded with with clearly employee
parking because that's where they're
parked
and it's just loaded. Very difficult.
Anyway, that's a concern of mine anyway.
Mr. Chair, through you. Um I am leaning
towards the the multifamily as well
forplex but I'm also um I think we need
to put the um the agriculture the urban
I think we need to have a better clear
definition and it shouldn't be towards
the bottom. I think it does need to be
up towards the top of our priority list.
Um I mean we do have some concerned you
know property owners that you know that
still don't that don't have a clear
vision or definition and I think we
should give them that opportunity as you
know as our comm as being commissioners
here.
Okay. Uh
would you guys like us to craft these
ideas into a single motion or just
acknowledge receipt and then let the I
don't know where are we going to have
minutes from this meeting? I presume
will they reflect the discussion?
Ideally if if there was a
you can acknowledge the receipt and we
we pretty much have inferred what you
all are are looking at what you all want
to see. Um, and we will have minutes
this meeting that will generally
upstate that. If if you would like, it
could be cleaner if you just stated
these are the items that you would like
to see us work on. And if everyone just
said their item clearly all in one
point, we can have that transcribed in
the minutes and then acknowledge receipt
of, you know, the presentation as
presented by staff and members of the
public today.
>> Yes. So, Mr. sure if I have at least
written down that there there's at least
three that I think
maybe four um that I've heard. So multif
family obviously being number one.
Um then we've got block size,
urban farm definition, and then there's
some concern with
Although I guess Commissioner Atha, is
it kind of you you want us to look at
the parking kind of removing parking
minimums or not removing?
>> I would like you to look at the parking
minimums to make sure he has some
provision for like this this business
complex. It's just I think twice before
I drive into it nowadays. So then
basically looking at parking minimums.
So multif family, block size, urban
farm, and parking minimums are the four
that I've heard. If all of you agree on
those, then you could put it into one
motion that you believe those are the
four that staff should really
kind of hard hit taking a look at this
year. Um I think that would work. Or if
you each want to say your individual
ones, you can do that as well. But um if
somebody wanted to do just the one
motion of acknowledging receipt and then
noting that the commission would like
staff to prioritize
multif family, block size, urban farm
definition, and parking minimums, we can
also go that route. I do have them
written down. Again, we'll have minutes
that should have this discussion in
there as well. So, but
somebody want to take a stab at a
motion? Boyd
>> Eric, one quick question for staff.
Sorry if I'm blanking, but what did
council did council give any directive
on these as well? I'm just curious if
we can maybe align a few of these or if
just to make sure that we're not sending
staff on a bunch of different
directions.
>> Chair, Commissioner Olsen, thanks for
for that. Um really we didn't get the
work session from the council was kind
of really focused on a multif family
that took a a lion share of the
development um discussion. So then
everything kind of got mushed together.
Um but what we heard from them um is to
look at the multif family but also to
look at how it could have design centers
to go with it. We've heard from them
that they're continuing to want us to
provide public outreach on landscaping,
um the requirements and the expectations
for landscaping, but to continue to move
forward with our in-house landscaping
code update, which we're working on
right now.
Um the
the parking minimums for non-residential
uses appear to be split. like we didn't
have a a clear uh thumbs up or thumbs
down. Um same with the carports and
front yards. Um and a lot of these were
ones that may have come from a council
member. So they may be seeing if they
can drum up other support to uh to see
who else wants to support that.
The
special uses um historic horse racing
facilities is a high priority of the
council. Uh that's sexually oriented
business one is a
um high priority of a few of the council
members. It's probably split.
The parking lot surfacing um is a
high priority one for the for the
council.
The attached sidewalks is a low
priority.
Um but it's still something they'd want
to some they would like to invest but
it's investigate but is a lower
priority.
The temporary construction uses is a um
a high priority from the council
block length. Uh that one seems to be a
medium level
uh priority. They're kind of dealing
with it as on a case- by case basis and
they're guaranteed to have more cases
coming up. So that's going to continue.
Zoning enforcement process is a low
priority from the council, high priority
from our zoning enforcement people, but
the council seem to be clear with that
being low priority lot types.
Uh that's a I probably say is a medium
priority, but I don't know if we can
adequately explain what that really
means to them. Um it really would make a
lot of processes high priority for
staff. This one is it was the end of the
meeting. It's low priority. It's it's a
lower priority one for them.
Um and based on discussions we've had
with the recent annexation um it appears
there's a high priority for the changes
related to agricultural uses.
I hope someone took notes on that.
>> Mr. Chair through you. Um, at the end of
your staff report, you had a a draft
motion. Could you put that up on the
screen? Yeah, maybe that would help us
get started.
>> Chair, I also think I might have a stab
at a motion if they'd be if people would
be willing to hear it.
>> Hold on a second, Lonnie. I just had one
more comment to make to follow up on
Charles last discussion. I while the
formbbased code is a low priority, it
also seems like kind of lowhanging
fruit. Uh if if there's no not much
opposition to it, just deleting that
article would be pretty quick and dirty.
>> Miss Mr. Chair through you. If as long
as we can kind of get everything in
order of where it's referenced
throughout the entire UDC, you're right.
It probably is lowhanging fruit. be
simple to just write an ordinance that
says we delete article 7 and all
references to it and just be done with
it. Um, but we do have to scour the UDC
to make sure we're getting all those
references
>> because the minute you delete article 7,
if you don't delete a reference, that
can also cause problems. So, but you're
right, if we can find all those, it
probably would be very simple to put
that together and bring that forward and
just be done with that all together. So
that might happen this year just because
it is low hanging fruit and easy.
>> Okay. If there's no other discussing, uh
I think I'll go back to Lonnie for his
proposed motion.
>> Uh chair through you. Uh
I move to acknowledge receipt of the
annual review report and further staff
to
uh priorities available time to
investigate the following uh the multif
family parking
urban farm and block length suggestions
provided in the annual review staff
report.
I second the motion.
>> Any discussion on the motion?
>> Uh, chair through I just want to make
sure that staff under is that acceptable
to them for that?
>> M chair through you. I would say that's
acceptable.
>> Okay.
Uh, if no other discussion, staff could
call the role.
Lonnie Olsen.
>> Hi.
>> Amy Hernandez.
>> Megan Connor.
>> Hi.
>> Bob Matia.
>> I
>> Boyd Wiggle.
>> Mr. Chair, that acknowledgement passes.
Okay, that concludes that uh part of the
agenda and the other uh next section is
other business and staff announcements.
So, I guess real quick before we hop
into number six on the agenda, um
just for I guess the public's benefit,
you do not have to feel don't feel that
you have to stick around for planning
commission training. um you're more than
welcome to uh hop out and leave. There
won't be any other business conducted.
It's just basically kind of annual
training we do for the planning
commission um for the planning
commission. Your next meeting, there
will be eight items on that agenda. So,
please, if you can be here for that
meeting, so we have a quorum. We have a
number of projects that I'm sure those
applicants would like moving forward. Um
I want to say all but two are actually
applicant uh applications.
One of them is kind of an applicant
application. It's the vacation of Frank
Court. If you remember that discussion
we had with the preliminary plat a
couple months ago. Um that vacation will
be coming forward for all of Frank
Court. So that kind of is applicant
driven um I guess but it's staff who's
doing the vacation. Um, and then you've
got Charles's text amendment
potentially, but otherwise, all the
applications on this agenda are
submitted by an applicant and they would
most likely want their projects moving
forward. But be prepared for a semi-
long agenda just with having eight items
on the on the agenda for that meeting.
Um, that's all I had for announcements.
I will be working on a new updated
version of the UDC. Uh the text
amendment for the
um
edus did get approved
by council.
Um so I do have to update the UDC again.
Um I do have it already drafted and
ready. I'm just waiting to make sure I
have the final ordinance before I
publish it. But the ADU uh text
amendment did get approved. So, be on
the lookout for another email just with
another copy of the UDC.
Um, as always, the UDC can be found
online. It's always the most up-to-date
version unless we're in this interim
time period where I have to update it
again. But other than that, I'll just
throw it over to Charles if he has any
other staff announcements before we hop
into the training.
>> Chair, another announcements. We're
going to jump into the training.
Chair, members of of of the commission,
this is a little bit more abbreviated
than usual or than the last ones you've
seen since most of us are aware of this.
So, it's not too uh not too indepth. So,
first of all, just uh note that our goal
is to um carry out the vision of the
comprehensive plan. State statute says
the planning commission shall develop a
plan for the community and then the the
planning commission serves as a
recommending body to the governing body
who implements the plan through
ordinances and such like the unified
development code.
Uh the plan the comprehensive plan is
available on our website. Again it's
multiple uh pieces of the comprehensive
plan. and it's our parks and recck
master plan, our transportation master
plan, and the community plan. Uh we
presently have funding to update the
community plan, and we're trying to get
that RFP or RF RFP out the door, but
things keep our other projects keep on
getting
getting brought up that we're working
on. Again, the unified development code
is what we see the most often here. Um,
it's the processes that are defined to
go from point A to point B in the
development world. Some are
administrative where they just go to
staff and they're done. Others do
require that they go in front of the
board of adjustment for approval or they
go to the governing body for approval
after review and recommendation by you
all, the planning commission.
We talked about the annual review
requirement today. Um that does happen
on the second meeting of every February
which falls on a Tuesday after the
president's day weekend.
Again the boards that you all are most
familiar with are the planning
commission which is you all guide growth
master plan primarily recommendations
the governing body uh the board of
adjustment. This is one that has some
decision-making authority. uh acting
chair led uh did serve on that for quite
some time. Um they hear appeals of um
administrative decisions. They also more
a final decision maker on variances and
conditional use uh approvals such as
uh apartments, complexes in certain zone
districts.
There are a variety of other um
commissions and boards and committees
that the the department does um have a
connection with, including specialty
committees like ATAC, the active
transportation advisory committee, which
I was meeting with prior to this
meeting, which they're probably still
meeting upstairs as well, or they just
got out.
No one showed up. I told them they could
share their ideas if they wanted to. Um
here's just a snapshot of what you all
do which you all are uh pretty
accustomed to knowing and we will try to
share with you anything new that pops
up. Uh things that are new are urban
renewal plans and projects recently and
DDA development projects. Those are ones
that you don't see as often but they do
uh make an appearance in front of you
all.
Public hearing process. This is pretty
straightforward. The applicant makes a
presentation. Then staff makes a
presentation, the staff report. The
planning commission can uh ask questions
of staff for the applicant. Then there's
public testimony, a public hearing. This
is the official public hearing in all of
our our uh zoning action items except
for annexations.
Those are in front of the governing body
and those happen at introduction of the
annexation ordinance. Um technically
once the public hearing is called closed
um then you all can move into
deliberation talk about how you want to
vote. You can ask staff for further uh
clarification if you wish. Um it's
strongly advised that you don't reopen
the public hearing as a chair to take on
more comment um just because that gets
to be a little bit bit squirly. It leads
to people easily being able to lose
control of the meeting. And with that in
mind, you know, if you do start asking
staff a lot of questions, sometimes the
uh the audience might feel that they
should have the ability to chime in. So,
if you do have uh questions on how
motion should be formed, please do it.
But if it's just general questions, try
to do that um either like while the
public hearing is active. During public
hearings, you are able to set time
limits as long as they are clearly noted
at the beginning of the public hearing
and they are consistent and they don't
change from a personto person basis.
>> Do you have the ability to track the
time? Do you have a countdown clock we
could use?
>> Yes, we do. We'd be able to figure that
out. And uh and one more question on the
previous slide about the uh public
hearing process and then leading into
planning commission deliberation in in u
I think we have another kind of little
step in there between when the hearing's
closed another chance for the applicant
to uh make additional comments if
there's something spurred on by the
public comments they can clarify or is
that correct? And technically, if there
is a condition that is made or something
that is modified,
um, you would be able to reopen the
public hearing to discuss that new
element only.
>> Yeah, I'm I'm specifically talking about
asking if the applicant would like to
come up and make additional comments
following the public hearing. It seems
like we do that.
>> Chair through to the commission. I
believe you all have done that before.
It's not necessarily a requirement.
So, it's if you all feel like that.
>> And then, Mr. Chair, I'll just add with
the time limits. Um, I think we've only
done a time limit at planning commission
once. Council does it all the time when
there's a ton of public comment. Um,
they actually did it last Monday for the
public hearing for the annexation. Um,
which I'm kind of happy they did because
it was two hours of testimony set at 3
minutes a piece for each person. So if
they didn't have a time limit, I don't
know when we would have been done with
that public hearing. Um so you are able
to if there is a lot of public and you
see a lot of public, you can as a
commission set a time limit to say, "All
right, we're going to set public comment
to three minutes so everybody has the
same amount of time to speak and we can
make it an efficient meeting." Um
because you've probably noticed with
certain public comment, it can turn into
a back and forth and it can turn into
just saying the same thing over and over
and over again. Um so having that time
limit does tend to keep people
on time. Um like Charles is doing to me
right now. Um but we do have the ability
to do time clocks and everything and
throw them up on the screen. And
>> a question, do you have to set that time
limit right at the beginning of the
public comments or can you sort of set
it in the middle of the public comments?
>> Mr. Chair, would have to be at the
beginning and council's done three
minutes. You could do five minutes. It's
kind of what you decide. I guess as a
commission um you could even maybe at
the beginning of every year maybe we set
something where we make a motion to for
this year we're going to set all public
comment to three minutes.
and we do it that way or something. I
mean, I don't know what Director Bloom's
take on that would be, but council has
done something where they have basically
said any public comment where there's a
lot of public, it's going to be set to
three minutes and they do that at any
council meeting where there is a ton of
public that has shown up for an item.
And chair there if there is three to the
commission if there is a large amount of
public we'll assist getting you to the
three minute one thing I note as I was
in another community when a council
member famously said should we turn on
the public comment timer for this person
that's not the right way to do it. You
want to have it uniformally um done. I
want y'all to know that I I did watch on
YouTube that council meeting from last
uh Monday night, like four and a half
hours long.
There's a 75minute executive session
after that, too.
All right. Um the department, it kind of
uh changes a little bit. I'm not
counting myself in here. We have four
planners that primarily report uh to
this commission. We have the MO director
who you'll see every once in a while um
who has staff members that will present
MO uh metropolitan planning organization
items. We have uh one primary planner
per project and then we have a staff
clerk um who is the essentially the
nickname for whoever is taking the
minutes. So that can be a planner that
can be our office manager who's in the
back. Um the commission composition you
all are pretty well aware of what we
have a chair a vice chair and a
secretary. The secretary is a sweet spot
because we do the minutes for you. So,
it's a it's a beautiful place to be in.
Uh board meetings generally the first
and third Mondays with a couple of
Mondays January and February is being
kicked midmon to Tuesdays because of uh
equality day, Martin Luther King Day and
also President's Day
and Memorial Day sometimes falls on a
Monday. No,
I think it's kicked our meeting once
before maybe. I don't know.
Um, our expectation of the board is we
want to make sure that you all are
running the meeting fairly and not to
lose control of of meetings. You all
haven't had anything majorly contentious
in a while where you've had a a audience
that's been out of control.
Even if you do support an item, you
know, personally and stuff, you know, re
be sure to maintain your composure. You
don't want to be agreeing with the
audience going, "Yeah, that's awesome,
Joey. I love you, Joey. that's the right
way to go. You don't want to want to do
that. You just want to be the
uninfluenced decision maker.
Uh respect respect staff and each other.
We haven't had any problems since 2018.
So, no, I'm just kidding. We haven't had
any problems with that, but just
remember to respect staff because a lot
of times people may have differing
viewpoints on different things. Um, we
ask that you're consistent in your um,
decisions, consistent in time limits,
and when you put time limits on folks
for public comment. And the other thing
that a lot of folks struggle with,
especially when you have public comment
that comes up to different meetings, is
you need to make sure that you're basing
your decisions on like the applicable
review criteria.
Um, this is a one-sizefits-all all slide
with our board of adjustment where they
they call it findings of fact. Um but
here we just need to make sure that they
meet the u review criteria. Um just
because something is generally opposed
by the public, you know, that's
that's very common that you're going to
see that argument a lot. Um a lot of
times as a planning commission, you're
simply making a recommendation to the
governing body.
They're the ones who have that paycheck,
although it's small. um they're the ones
who are getting paid as the electors to
make those political decisions that are
more based on the um public comment. So,
it's it's always best to uh try to stick
to the to the review criteria and public
comment is one that should be
incorporated. Um but just a general
opposition because of the usual uh
things we hear. It's too much traffic.
It's going to decrease property values.
is going to block my view of this
that intersections
done. It's going to flood my property.
You know, those are ones we're going to
hear on almost every project and those
should be taken. Um, not saying they
should be dismissed, but they should not
be the only factor in your decisions.
Um, so we come in the meetings, we
usually understand what's going to
happen, but sometimes we leave and we're
like, "Okay, that happened." But
whatever your recommendation is, um, our
role as staff is to carry forward your
recommendation to the governing body for
approval. So, say you modify text
amendment
Tuesday morning or Wednesday morning, we
have to turn it around to the governing
body. We get with our city attorney's
office, the other departments and
divisions that may be affected, and we
have to reddraft that ordinance. And we
will clearly state that in a cover memo.
this is how it changed at planning
commission and these are the reasons why
or this is the reason they recommended
you deny it was for these solid reasons.
So, whenever you do say something's
getting denied, tell us why. Um because
just trying to understand your
discussion isn't going to be enough. And
if it does happen to make it through
like an appeals process or go to court,
um they want to see those those reasons
why clearly um pinpointed and how they
relate to that review criteria.
Um staff report preparation. You've seen
our staff reports. Um, I think we have a
pretty good format right now. Um, I
believe I've given uh Mr. Lloyd a little
bit more room because he wants to put
some more images in there. So, you might
see some changes upcoming with our our
formats. Um, but again, we're pulling
all of our um items
uh from our unified development code,
specifically our review criteria. Every
time we have an application, it clearly
states review criteria and we end that
subsection by saying as condition this
item meets the review criteria or this
meets it or this doesn't. Um typically
when something goes through the process
to the planning commission, we're going
to bring something that meets the review
criteria whether it's by conditions um
or by what they submitted.
So everything has a reason like that
sign. No monkeys or there's monkeys
ahead. Really? Roll up your windows.
There's monkeys. So, there's re there's
reasons for that.
>> Uh, chair, I do have a comment on that
last slide. I do want to appreciate I do
appreciate what staff has added in this
past year within their staff reports. Uh
they have added that public comment
section which I do appreciate because
that was a I believe it was a common
question that would come up amongst all
of us is if they have had any public
comments amongst the advertised period
and I do just think that's kind of a
nice section to have within those. So
kudos to staff for adding that.
>> Thank you Commissioner Olsen. And what
we do do with public comment is we try
to be neutral on that is if we'll say we
have received five comments from the
neighbors. Generally they have been
opposed to the project for reasons such
as um traffic and blah blah blah. But
we're going to say more like perceptions
around or it's not going to say because
traffic is going to increase because we
don't really know if that's a true
statement that's going to create a a
negative um
have a negative influence on that
project.
So again, I went over the review
criteria, why they're important. Again,
stick to the facts. You don't want to be
saying no to a project just because you
wanted a a Starbucks and they're
proposing a
caribou coffee.
Export communications. This is one that
um we talk about a lot. Um this is when
you all and we have a disclosures
portion at the beginning of every agenda
that rolls for a department. Um, it's
basically to disclose if you've been
made privy to specific information
that's generally not available to the
other commission members um or uh to
staff. So, this could be maybe one of
you was given a
a map for a plat for reasonzoning saying
this is what I intend to build here. So,
this is why you should vote yes.
and
it's something that is unique and
privileged to you. If that happens, you
need to disclose it. I mean, you need to
make sure that that is known by by
everybody.
Um, I share this every year. I don't
know if you all have memorized it or
remember it. So, this one says, "Do you
think I should reveal these
conversations we're having as exparte
communication?" Nonsense. You're just
spending the weekend here relaxing in my
pool. We aren't talking shop. You know,
it it happens at times, especially in a
small town.
>> Charles, in that disclosure section at
the beginning, is that the time to uh
say we have a conflict of interest on
one of the items and we would like to be
excused when it comes time for that.
>> Okay. that also.
Uh oh,
here that is correct. Yes, that would be
the appropriate time.
That would be the appropriate time to
identify if you have a conflict of
interest, which I'll just jump to that
really quick. So, a conflict of interest
is a situation in which an individual
has competing interests or loyalties.
Let's use uh Commissioner Olsen for
example. Um let's say he's starting a
bicycle shop in town and he needs to
reszone a property in the middle of his
neighborhood to community business or
even light industrial because he just
wants different building standards so he
can operate his business. It would not
be appropriate for Lonnie to take a a
vote on that item because he has a
demonstrated conflict of interest
because there's conflicting loyalties
there. for him it would be best that he
would leave the room um and then have
someone else present that project on his
behalf. Same thing is if um you all had
a sister or a brother or a mother or a
son and they were asking for
um a specific recommendation for
approval, you want to avoid avoid that
because there's a perception of
favoritism there. And also if you are
partners in a real estate group
um and you have a potential financial
gain because of this action that would
be a concern as well. Those would be
conflicts that you would note and then
you would be excused from voting on
those items. We haven't had too many
conflicts um on this board but uh we
have on a couple of others where they've
um abstained from voting and recuse
themselves. But we do ask that they do
leave the room, you know, during that
vote because even your presence, your
mannerisms, just your just being there,
it could have um an effect on the board.
Commissions, boards, and committees
aren't the best at leaving the room.
Sometimes they sit there and I'm like,
"A weren't you listening during
training?" So,
um, open meetings act. This is something
that is very important. Um, this doesn't
mean that, you know, six of you are
hanging out at a holiday party. You
know, you happen to run in a holiday
party together. It's when you're
starting to conduct public business.
So, you all could all be hanging out at
some different event because you're
volunteering for planning month in
October. You know, you're serving
chicken wings for everybody or something
like that. you know, you could all be
together, but the moment you're like,
"Oh, let's talk about this new apartment
complex that's proposed and you start to
have something that would resemble what
would be discussed here, that's where
the issue is issue is. Um, so if you
have a quorum of people, a quorum of
board members, they're talking about a
board topic, you have an issue. But if
you have a less than quorum and say
you're studying something like block
length amendments, you have less than a
majority, you know, you could have a
subcommittee that could talk freely and
private there and then you would report
back to the whole planning commission
what your findings are.
So I've uh
kind of reduced um my take on this. I
always operate under extreme caution and
said avoid a quorum being present at all
times. But now I've loosened it to just
say just don't talk business if you're
having more of a quorum um present. Now
this includes things like Facebook
posts,
uh text message strings, email
correspondence.
Um try not to hit reply all and
definitely don't start talking about
um an upcoming agenda item on any of
those those items. This is another good
one. I haven't seen this motion yet. I
think it'd be funny if I did. All those
in favor of what we discussed in our
email thread at Larry's son's birthday
party say, "I I I
have no idea what's going on. I thought
this meeting was open."
So, open meetings are important.
Uh, we have a development map online,
which does it still look like this,
Connor?
No, this has been retired. This um was
our second development map and we
recently retired it. Now we have a new
development map called Connect Cheyenne.
This covers all of our uh site plans
that we have submitted. So you people
can thumb around on Connect Cheyenne.
There's a map view and there's also a
list view where you can see things that
don't come in front of you. Like for
example, a new Seven Brew being built in
town. You'll be able to see where that
coffee shop is located. You'll be able
to look at the site plan documents for
the Rocky Mountain car wash on Ridge
Road. The Wells Fargo Bank at IHOP is on
there. Correct.
the Dunkin Donuts that Albertson says is
back and that's on
most of the stuff I have been putting on
there has been um
kind of our public meeting ones, ones
that we actually have public comment on
the site plans have been a little uh
backlogged on and haven't been putting
up as much unless they're very prominent
kind of developments that we get
questions on. So like data centers, not
putting them up there, things like that.
Um but yes, for like the Dunkin Donuts
that's proposed over off of Persing um
in front of Albertson's, that one's on
there. That one's been on there for a
while. I've been working through some
stuff. Um but most of the time I'm
putting up anything that has to do with
a public meeting. Um just so it has
another form of kind of being put out
there. Um, I didn't do so much of that
with the county pocket annexations
because those were a very wide range and
with the map I was trying to pinpoint
specific where these specific projects
are, um, county pockets were kind of all
over the place. But generally when we
have kind of these public
uh, public meeting ones, board of
adjustment and planning commission,
those projects are up there. So people
kind of know if there's a zone change, a
plat
conditional use, things like that.
>> Yeah. And and chair, members of of the
commission for county pocket uh
annexations, we had a landing page
specifically for all the residents that
were involved because they were the ones
that needed to have that communication
directly available to them. Um we are
hoping to
get our public facing side of things
better. Uh, we have our permit software
that's out there. Um, we're still
working through some kinks with getting
the right information out there to be
public. Um, and I do want to note that
we do have a lot of these data center
developments that are coming through.
Their site plans are generally public
site plans that you can see, but when
you start to look at the building permit
and the actual floor layout and what's
going on inside, those are proprietary
and those are held back because they are
proprietary and industry.
um secrets for lack of a better term.
They're all doing their own little deal.
So that we don't share those things just
like we're not going to share permits
for federal buildings or security
buildings, stuff like that. So those are
are withheld.
So we're trying to be open and and get
everything out there. Again, we still
have our panda, Pat the Planning Panda.
It was named before Mayor Collins was
here, but it's Pat the Planning Panda.
So that's it. That concludes our
streamlined annual review.
>> I I have a little question about public
information. I I love the GIS map and I
drill into that on individual properties
that I'm just curious about, not
necessarily development stuff, but what
I've seen some lately is uh where the
ownership is withheld and I I guess I
wonder why that is. Is that is that not
public information that should be on
there? and chair, members of the
commission, anyone can make a request to
the county assessor to have their
ownership information withheld. We do
know who those people are though. I mean
I mean there's there's a handful of them
>> and there's there's a way you can fi
figure it out pretty quickly when you
look at the mailing address and then put
that mailing address in and track it to
the parent parcel of where that mailing
address goes and see the name on there
or it yeah it can be very easy to figure
out these owner name withheld ones.
So,
I mean it it at least for businesses, I
guess if it's a singular ownership, like
if I withheld my name on my property,
you probably would never know. Um, but
for these larger businesses that do it,
it it's very easy to figure out. We're
very aware of one of them that has done
it.
All
right, chair. Uh, members of the
commission, any other further comments?
Right. Thank you for your your patience
and um listen to everything today.
>> So, that's all the business we're
adjourned. Thank you.